This is an introduction to the software XModeler.
In case you don't have a link to the download
page, you can search it yourself; you go to
some search engine, you type in this.
This is the page.
This is a tutorial and some explanations
by the people who created the software.
And I'm going to go to the download section.
I'm going to download this file,
and I'm going to open the tutorials.
Despite the first one.
This tutorial gives you two
options on how to run XModeler.
I'm going to go for option number two.
And for this, the first thing you need to
do is to install Java JDK on your computer.
And it does not matter if it's an 8, like in
option number 1, or if it's a later version.
And since I am on Windows, I'm going to go
here.
So, what you do is you download any
of these files and you install it.
And it's very straightforward; it's simple
to do.
Now let's go back to the tutorial.
You also need JavaFX, and there is a link
here.
Let's click this link.
Scroll down.
And then again I am on Windows.
So, I'm going to download this one.
Now I have these two files
in my downloads folder.
I'm going to take them to some folder that I
created, an empty folder, and just paste it
here and extract. Now let's
go back to the tutorial.
And now we have XModeler.bat file adjustment.
And this is a file that we need
because we are working on Windows.
This is the file they are talking about.
And you're going to edit it; you can do it
like this with a default text editor that
you have, with any text editor.
I'm going to do it with Notepad++.
And it tells you that you need to find this
line.
They are actually talking about
this line; it is a bit different.
And then you replace this part
with the path to this folder.
You go here to library, you copy
this path, you replace this.
And of course, don't forget to put your
path inside quotation marks like this.
And now save the file and close it.
Let's try to run XModeler.
And as you can see, it is working.
Create a project; call it whatever.
And now you have the project here; left click.
Now you have it here.
You have the Models; you click Create Diagram.
Call it whatever.
Click OK, and now this diagram is here;
you double click it and it's open.
Now you can create a diagram.
There are many features in XModeler that we are
not going to use because they are irrelevant
for us in this course.
So, I'm just going to show you the basics.
To create a class, you right click,
you choose Add, you click class.
And then let's call it A, for example.
And then you have this level field here.
Just put 1 whenever you are creating a class
and put 0 whenever you're creating anything
else.
So, click OK.
And now the cursor changes because the program
is now ready for you to click and place the
class that you just created.
And I left click here.
This is the class.
This is class A. So, we don't care about the
level; we don't care about that it says it's
a meta class.
We just care that this is a class now.
Now let's create class B. Make it level 1.
And as soon as I click outside of this field,
I can choose to make it inherit from class
A. If I click OK now and I place it, it creates
this inheritance arrow automatically, and
it connects them.
Let's create another one.
Click OK, place it here.
And we can make C inherit from B. Even after
creating the class, you do this by right clicking,
and then change parent.
And then let's choose B. Click OK.
And it creates an arrow automatically.
If you mess with the levels of the elements
that you're creating, let's say for example,
you have 2 here instead of 1 or you have 0
or whatever, and then you might face some
problems; you cannot—for example, you cannot
make C inherit from B. So, just stick to
what I said: do 1s for classes
and 0 for everything else.
And of course, it gets messy; sometimes you
see, the arrows are kind of stuck to each
other, so we need to separate them.
To do this, first, I'm going to move this
class here because this line is not connected.
from this side, it's actually connected from
this side where you see this black dot.
So, move it like this.
And this one is connected from the top
and from the bottom at the same time.
So, what I'm going to do is left-click and
hold on this line, move it to the side and
release.
Now this arrow is separated;
this is the same for this one.
Good, it's separated now.
So, move this one here, just to make it
look a bit better, a bit easier to read.
Okay, now let's do other classes; let's
create Class D, level 1, put it here.
Class E at level 1, put it here.
And now let's say I would like an association
between E and D. You can either right-click
and add Association.
Or you can do Association from here; just
left-click once, do not hold, just left-click,
and then the cursor changes.
You go from E to D, for example.
And left-click and then no holding, no dragging,
just left-click and release and then left
click again.
And you have this window.
So, let's call the association and you have
to call it; you have to fill in these fields,
you cannot leave them empty.
So, let's call this association small x.
And it starts from E and it ends in D. And
this is the level that I just talked about.
So, here you put 0 because
we're not creating classes.
And you leave everything here as
it is; it's not important for us.
And these two options are the ones
that decide the navigation arrow.
The arrow that tells you whether this object
of this class knows an object from the other
class or not.
So, for now, I'm going to do this; I'm going
to check these two boxes, and these are the
multiplicities.
Now you can change.
Let's say I would like to
have multiplicity 2 to 5 here.
Click OK.
And then here, let's do 0 to star.
So, I removed the upper limit; I click OK.
Now click OK.
And I have the association created now.
And these errors are because of the checkboxes
that I told you about, the ones that say,
target visible from source and
source visible from target.
So, let's remove this one, for example.
Click OK.
And you have just one arrowhead
here but no arrowhead here.
This is the reading direction.
It always sticks to the name of the association.
So, this is the name that we chose.
This is the x.
You can move this around; you cannot move
these around; you move them, but they go back
to their position.
But this is fine, it's easy to read.
And this 0 here is the
level that we just entered.
We don't care about this.
This 0 here is similar to this one
here; don't get confused by it.
And this software also shows you some
methods, some operations like this.
If you don't want to see these get operations,
just go here, to this one, uncheck this box.
And now it looks clean and simple.
Now, let me continue with this example.
So, first, let me edit, just change some things.
For example, here, this multiplicity,
I would like to change it.
So, I'm going to double-click on
this line on this association.
And let me change instead of 0 to star.
Let's do 1 to 1, okay?
So, now we have 1 here; we have 2 to 5.
And now let's create some objects.
So, I'm going to create an object diagram.
And XModeler is going to verify; it's going
to tell you whether there is a problem.
Whether my object diagram that I'm creating
conforms to this class diagram or not.
So, I'm going to move my mouse cursor here
to the top, and then scroll down to zoom
out, scroll down with my
mouse, and then zoom in here.
Actually, you can do like this;
you can navigate here as well.
But I prefer this way; I prefer
to zoom out and then zoom in.
And now let's create some objects.
Actually, to make it simple, let me go back
here and change this multiplicity again.
So, instead of one, let's do zero to star.
This is fine.
And here, let's do one to two.
Now let's create something, an instance
of E. Call it small e, click OK.
Place it.
So far, so good; no problems.
And now let's create an instance of D. You
can do this; you can do as I just did: right-
click and add instance.
But you can also right-click
this the class that you want.
And you create an instance of this class,
right-click, and then add instance.
So, let's keep it d1 is fine.
Let's keep the name small d, and 1, click
OK.
Place it as soon as you place it says: “This
d1 that he just created needs to be linked
to an instance of E.” So, you can
ignore this issue; you can click OK.
So, nothing happens except that
there's still a complaint here.
If you double-click again,
you get the window again.
I mean, if you double-click it, if you would
like to see the window again, you just double
click here, you have this window.
And you can either create a new instance of
E, or you can link to an instance that you
already have.
So, we already have an E here; behind
this window, you cannot see it.
So, choose it.
Click OK.
And it's linked.
And I didn't even have to do anything manually.
I didn't have to say what kind of association
this is because it recognizes, XModeler looks
here and sees that a D is connected to
an E through an association called x.
So, it automatically adds this x with the
same reading direction and the same navigation
direction.
And it links them.
So, does this fulfill the multiplicities?
Yes.
So, in fact, what happened is that this multiplicity
here, it's basically saying, whenever you
have something of type D, you have to have
at least one thing, one instance of E and
this instance, at least 1 instance
and at most 2 instances, okay?
And these one or two instances have to be
connected to this D with an x association.
And this is exactly what we have here.
So, this means we can add
another E. Let's do that.
Let's add an instance call it e2 for example.
Placed here.
And then I'm going to manually connect d1
to e2.
You can do it by left-clicking here and
then left-clicking here, left-clicking here.
And since there are no options, the only choice
that XModeler has is to recognize the link
that you just created as an x association.
This is the only thing possible
according to this class diagram.
So, it does it, recognizes it like this and
it connects it and again this is the reading
direction; this is the navigation arrow.
And this object diagram
conforms to this class diagram.
Of course, it conforms to everything that we
have here, but here there are no limitations
concerning E and D objects.
In this upper part of the class diagram.